בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. And today's דף Daf is ס"ח, Samach-Chet,
which as you could see is a relatively small one because it
is we it's a little complicated in terms of dealing with the
issue of קינים, Kinnim, which as we said is the whole מסכת
Masechet in the end of זבחים Zevachim that only has משנה, Mishnah,
no גמרא, Gemara, and it's all about mixing up the bird sacrifices.
Usually a חטאת Chatas and an עולה Olah that are brought when
a woman gives childbirth is a classic example. And then what happens
if they get mixed up and done in the wrong way? And
it also has this interesting indeterminacy about it because the woman could
bring the two of them and let the כהן Kohen decide which
is which. So the גמרא Gemara is bringing in this discussion because
it was in the context of the position of רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua who said that if an עולה Olah is done below as
a חטאת, Chatas, a bird עולה, Olah, that it doesn't have מעילה.
Me'ilah. And the גמרא Gemara assumed that that meant that it actually
transformed into a חטאת. Chatas. And it brought evidence from קינים Kinnim
that it didn't really transform into a חטאת. Chatas. And now the
גמרא Gemara is like demonstrating that the author of קינים Kinnim is
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So it's going to get to the punchline,
which we read yesterday, which is fine. So קינים Kinnim is רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and from קינים Kinnim you can prove that the
עולה Olah doesn't turn into a חטאת. Chatas. So רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua never said it turns into a חטאת. Chatas. He said if
you do it like a חטאת, Chatas, there's no מעילה. Me'ilah. It's
enough in the חטאת Chatas category that there's no מעילה. Me'ilah. We
discussed whether or not the כהנים Kohanim would be able to eat
the meat. Presumably yes, who knows. But anyway, his fundamental point was
that there was no מעילה, Me'ilah, but you're right, from קינים Kinnim
you can demonstrate that it doesn't genuinely turn into a חטאת. Chatas.
So that was like the end of that arc, but now we
are in the middle of a complicated משנה Mishnah in קינים, Kinnim,
and the purpose of bringing it in is not so much to
analyze it, but to get to the punchline at the end where
it sounds like the authorial voice is רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So
the גמרא Gemara doesn't really analyze it at all. The גמרא Gemara
just cites it, but we are going to now with רש"י's Rashi's
help understand what the heck this משנה Mishnah is talking about. So
alright, so let's start again and we'll do a little we'll do
a little re-beginning of it from what we read yesterday. So ס"ז
עמוד ב', Samach-Zayin Amud Bet, תא שמע, Tashma, it is ten lines
from the bottom, there's an asterisk in the middle of the line,
תא שמע. Tashma. So here's this משנה Mishnah in קינים Kinnim where
we're not going to analyze it at all in the גמרא, Gemara,
but the point is going to be the punchline at the end
that shows that the authorial voice is רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So
תא שמע: Tashma: האישה שאמרה הרי עלי קן אם אלד זכר. Ha-ishah
she-amrah Harei Alai Kan, Im eiled zachar. So a
woman says,
"I
will
bring two birds if
I give birth to a" wait, are we sure? Hold on. Okay,
fine. "I will bring two birds if I give birth to a
male." And when a woman makes a נדר, Neder, both are an
עולה. Olah. The only time it's a חטאת Chatas is actual her
obligation for childbirth. ילדה זכר מביאה שתי קינים. Yalda zachar, mevia shetei
kinnim. So she gave birth to a male, fine. Now she brings
two pairs of birds. אחת לנדרה ואחת לחובתה. Achas lenidrah veachas lechovatah.
One for her נדר, Neder, her vow, which is two עולות, Olahs,
and one for her obligation. נתנתן לכהן. Netanatan lakohen. Now she gave
it to the כהן. Kohen. So the כהן Kohen has to do
three above, okay, הכהן צריך
לעשות שלוש למעלה ואחת למטה, Hakohen tzarich la'asot shalosh lema'lah veachas lematah,
three above, there are three עולות, Olahs, and one below, there's one
חטאת. Chatas. לא עשה כן. Lo asa chen.
The כהן Kohen assumed a woman gives me two sets of birds,
they're for two sets of childbirths, half go above, half go below.
He assumed it was one of these cases of dealer's choice, כהן's
Kohen's choice, where basically the woman didn't designate which was which, so
he just of each pair, he put one above and one below.
One became an עולה, Olah, one became a חטאת. Chatas. Okay? אלא
עשה שתים למעלה ושתים למטה. Ela asa shtayim lema'lah veshtayim lematah. ולא
נמלך, Velo nimlach, he didn't ask. צריך שתביא עוד פרידה אחת ותקריבה
למעלה ממין אחד. Tzarich shetavi od preidah achat vetakrivah lema'lah mimin echad.
So if they're all of the same, they're all תור Tor or
בני יונה, Bnei Yonah, they're all turtledoves or pigeons, so then she
has to just bring so let's assume they're all, I don't know,
תורים, Torim, okay, so she went ahead and
the כהן Kohen did two above and two below. Now the other
הלכה Halacha that I forgot to mention yesterday is that the first
set, רש"י Rashi says this at least, the first set is always
defined as the חובה, Chovah, as the חטאת Chatas עולה Olah pair.
Okay? So she did set one and then she did set two.
All right? She, he, excuse me, the כהן. Kohen. So the first
set, fine, that was done properly, חטאת Chatas and עולה. Olah. It
was supposed to be a חטאת Chatas and עולה. Olah. The second
set, okay, only one of them is the they were both supposed
to be עולות, Olahs, but only one of them was made as
an עולה. Olah. So what do you have to do? You have
to bring one more עולה, Olah, okay, very simple, and I'm obviously
a תור. Tor. The other הלכה Halacha is that if you're bringing
a second of a pair, it also always has to be paired
with the first in the terms of the same type of bird.
Okay? So if it's all the same type of bird, then the
second set, both were supposed to be above, only one was, bring
one more. Okay, so that's that line. So it says, צריך שתביא
Tzarich shetavi again, four lines from. On the bottom, שתביא עוד פרידה
אחת, she-tavi od preda achat, one bird, a פרידה preda is a
single bird, a קן kan or קן ken I should say is
two birds, ותקריבנה למעלה, v'takrivenna lemala, and she brings it above, she
brings it עולה olah that she missed out on, ממין אחד. mimin
echad. That's if it all came from the same. ומשני מינים, umeshnei
minim, now let's say, however, there was תור tor and בני יונה.
bnei yonah.
The כהן kohen didn't ask her
which is which, you know, what's the story with this, is it
a נדר, neder, is it a this, he just worked on his
own assumptions. Right, that's how most problems happen in life, that we
don't ask, we just assume things. Of course, then we don't know
that we're half the time we don't know we're assuming because it's
so obvious, why should we ask? Anyway, okay, so he did this,
two above and two below. Now, again, following רש״י, Rashi,
you would say, okay, fine, this is what you did, bring one
more בן יונה, ben yonah, right? Because if your second one is
your is your נדר, neder, so you have you brought one of
your עולה olah of your נדר, neder, one you did wrong, bring
a second בן יונה. ben yonah. But רש״י Rashi says also, the
כהן kohen doesn't remember which one he did first and which one
he did second. So since the כהן kohen doesn't remember which one
he did first and which one he did second, we know that
you have to pair the second one according is is the נדר
neder pair is the נדר, neder, okay, and you have to so
you have to do the other pair of the נדר, neder, but
you don't know which is the first, which is the second. So
therefore if this is the first, then you bring one more בן
יונה, ben yonah, if this is if this is the first and
the תור tor is the second, then you bring one more תור,
tor, since you don't know which it is, you gotta bring one
תור tor and one one בן יונה ben yonah for your עולה.
olah. Okay, so ומשני מינים תביא שתים. umeshnei minim tavi shtayim. Okay,
that's the first case. Second case: פירשה נדרה. pirshah nidrah. When she
took a vow, she said, I am going to bring two birds
as an עולה, olah,
and I really like בני יונה bnei yonah so they're going to
both be בני יונה. bnei yonah. Okay, but again, all of this
is a lot missing here, it's all being filled in by רש״י.
Rashi.
But then she forgot. Comes the time, you know, that it actually
is that, oh, it's time to bring my קרבן, korban, I remember
I said, I was thinking, should it be תור, tor, בן יונה,
ben yonah, I can't remember which way I decided, but I said
one of them. Okay, so before you even get to mixing it
up, what does she have to bring now? What she has to
bring, just to satisfy her doubt, right, is she's got to go
ahead and bring number one is whatever the heck she wants because
she didn't explicate, that's just her obligation. Okay, so number one, her
חובה chovah for her childbirth, I don't care what it is. You
could do תור תור tor tor or you could do בן יונה
בן יונה, ben yonah ben yonah, we'll just assume תור תור. tor
tor. Okay, number one do whatever the heck you want. But now,
she doesn't remember what she said number two would
be. Okay, so even assuming the כהן kohen doesn't mess anything up,
just because she's confused in her own head, she's got to bring
two
more sets. Okay,
right, because she knows she promised one of those sets and she
doesn't remember which one. Okay, so she comes to the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash with three sets. And if the כהן kohen were to
ask and she were to think to tell, the כהן kohen would
do the first set above and below, and the second two sets
all above. Okay, that's that scenario. פירשה נדרה, pirshah nidrah, so she
explicated.
And she knows that she vowed to bring two, let's say she
just had to bring one תור? tor? She knows she brings two.
How does that fit in the words?
She was מפרש mefareish at the time of the נדר, neder, and
you're supposed to understand that מפרש mefareish at the time of the
נדר neder means explicated what type of bird.
That's why צריכה להביא עוד ג׳ פרדים.
tzricha lehavi od gimel preidim. So now, the first scenario, okay, ממין...
now, צריכה להביא tzricha lehavi עוד ג׳ פרדים ממין א׳. So now,
but now what we're doing is, we're not describing what the default
would have been. Okay, this is like you have to assume this
is true. And you have to assume that she forgot which one,
right? Like there's a lot of assumptions. So but now what happened
was, the next line צריכה Tzricha. להביא is in this scenario, she
then the כהן kohen went ahead and he just assumed that everything
was everything was, you know, they were all whatever, you know,
they were all part of a חובה. chovah. Okay, so now what
does she have to do? Well, it's פשוט. pashut. Let's take a
look. He brought this, this is right, okay,
these are half right, so you would think that she only has
to bring one תור tor and one בן יונה. ben yonah. So
why is it three? Hold on. You know, I can't tell you
how many times I read this and then as soon as I
then it all flies out of my head. Okay, anyway, hold on.
There's a note here explaining.
Wait, wait, wait, let me... okay, it's okay, I'm sure it does
but I need to understand myself. Hold on.
Okay. Okay, we've
got one, two, three up here. Here's two, the first pair was
her
obligation.
Oh no, no, because Rashi, that's the point I was missing. He
didn't bring three. Right. There you go. Thank you. Okay, that was
the point I was missing. This is what she's obligated. But she
סתם stam did, she went ahead and she just brought two pairs.
Okay? Right? She just figured like she didn't remember, she figured I
don't remember, I'll just bring whichever one I want. Okay, so that's
the other piece of the information that's missing. Okay, so this is
ממין אחד. mimin echad. She just brought two pairs and
and now the question is and the Cohen did half above half
below, what's what's the obligated? So compare this to this. So what
you're missing, so what you got here is this was correct, this
was correct. So now what you're missing is one more תור tor
and two more בני יונה. benei yona. That's actually quite straightforward. Okay?
Got it? So she was supposed to do this, but she only
brought two pairs and then the other problem was the Cohen did
both halves above and half below. So you've got only one good
out of the four that are needed here. Right, that's actually quite
straightforward. Okay, so צריכה שתביא, tzricha she-tavi, where are we? פירשה צריכה
שתביא עוד ג' פרדים ממין אחד. pirsha tzricha she-tavi od gimmel peradim
mimin echad. That's if it's all of one type. ומב' מינים, u-mib'
minim, now let's say that this was
these the two that she brought were two types, בן יונה ben
yona and בן יונה. ben yona. So now you would think, okay,
same story. Bring one בן יונה ben yona and two תור. tor.
Same story, right? But the other part that's missing here of the
description is we don't know which was first, which was second and
of the the order that the Cohen brought them in. And Rashi
again says, so that's one point, and Rashi again says the only
the first one is always the חובה chova and the second one
is always the נדר. neder. So if you don't if this was
first if this was first
and the בן יונה ben yona was second, you need one בן
יונה ben yona and two תור. tor. If it was the reverse,
then you need one תור tor and two בני יונה. benei yona.
So the result is you need two of each. Okay? Because you
don't know which is the מין min that you need two of
and which is the מין min that you need one of.
Why wouldn't we say that in the case before too?
Because in the case before it was all תור, tor, so you
know you had one תור. tor. Okay? So, okay.
So ומב' מינים, u-mib' minim, if it's if these are two sets
and again we don't know which was first, which was second, and
it's the second one that is the נדר, neder, so תביא ארבע.
tavi arba. Then she has to bring four because at the end
of the day you need you know you need you don't know
which whether you've satisfied one תור tor or one בן יונה. ben
yona. Since you don't know which one you satisfied, you have to
bring all four. קבעה נדרה. kava nidra. Now קבעה kava is more
than פירשה. pirsha. What קבעה kava means is she said, again you
have to know all of this or you have to read Rashi.
So what קבעה נדרה kava nidra means, she said I'm going to
bring a something, a נדר, neder, she said explicitly what תור, tor,
בן יונה, ben yona, she doesn't remember what. It's the same previous
case and she said, and I'm going to bring it together with
my obligation.
And when she says together with my obligation,
what that means is is that all of the עולות olot at
least have to come together. So in if she was doing it
right now that she's set a specific one and she doesn't remember
which one she said, but she also said it's going to be
קובע koveia with the נדר, neder, it means that all of these
have to be brought at the same time. So if she was
missing like you know some of them, she can't just like make
up the ones she's missing, it has to like all be done
at the same time. So let's take a look what that means.
So why can't she bring all the ones she's missing at the
same time? What? So she could bring all the ones she's missing
at the same time.
She can bring everything she's missing. Yes, but she was קובע koveia
together with this. So she can't bring it separate from this.
But if she was יוצא yotzei with the חובה, chova, can't she
now try to redo her נדר? neder?
So that seems to be right. So so that seems to be
the difference of קבעה. kava. That קבעה kava requires, and let's see
how it plays out, that that קבעה kava requires that it somehow
come at the same time with this. So if she did only
one of these, then you know she might have to do all
five again because she sort of said I'm bringing it together as
one big unit, as one big like קרבן גדול, korban gadol, but
it's
not מעכב meakev on the the חובה. chova. Like she was יוצא.
yotzei.
Oh, she was יוצא yotzei this? Oh right, correct. Correct.
And in terms of numbers that's
correct, and what's going to happen is, that is correct, the חובה
chova was and this is I might as well say this now,
it's an interesting like part of the הלכה. halacha. Let's she went
ahead and she brought this. And then she I don't know didn't
do anything or messed this up or whatever. Because she was קובע
koveia as one big thing, she has to bring both, that's all
just part of her נדר, neder, right? She as soon as she
brought this she was she fulfilled her obligation. Even if she said
this is my נדר, neder, this was still her obligation. So now
it's actually quite funny because if we're going to bring another תור
tor to make it feel like you can to make it like
you got one big קרבן korban of all this stuff together, but
this other תור tor here is not your obligatory one. You already
fulfilled your obligation as soon as you did this. So okay, you
messed this up, you gotta do all this again. So there's so
the funny הלכה halacha here is that we can sort of make
this correspond to. Since she was קובע, koveya, it was all supposed
to come together, maybe sort of like, you know, if you missed
it, if you did this and you didn't do that right, okay,
then do all the עולות olos again and one עולה ola will
correspond to the עולה ola of the obligation. Even though you already
fulfilled the עולה ola of your obligation, okay, it's going to that's
how it has to play out in order for you to satisfy
your נדר. neder. And it has to be the same type of
your obligation, okay?
Alright. צריכה.
Tzricha, Incidental, because we're just we're just trying to prove this whether
it's
completely incidental, but it's in the גמרא, Gemara, so we're explaining it.
We already got to the end yesterday. Okay. צריכה, tzricha when else
would we get a chance to discuss קינים Kinnim except when we
get to קינים? Kinnim? Okay,
צריכה שתביא עוד חמש פרידים למעלה ממין אחד ומב' מינים תביא שש.
Tzricha shetavi od chamesh peridim lemala mimi-echad umibais minim tavi shesh. So
she has to now bring five above, and if there's two there's
six. Why does she have to bring five above? So let's say
again it was all this, this is what she actually brought. Okay,
it was all this. Okay, so bottom line is it doesn't really
matter. Since she didn't bring all five all of this at the
same time, right? Right, this is what she brought. But it doesn't
matter. She was obligated to do all of this at the same
time, so she didn't. So none of the none of the נדר
neder counts. If none of the נדר neder counts, what does she
do? She does what we just said. She's got to bring all
five. You don't get credit for the one for the one תור
tor of the נדר. neder. It all has to come at the
same time with the obligatory one. So since you needed two תורים
torim and you didn't know maybe you needed two בני יונה, benei
yona, you gotta bring all five. Okay, so that's line number one.
צריכה שתביא עוד חמש פרידים למעלה מזה, Tzricha shetavi od chamesh peridim
lemala mizeh, that's if it's ממין אחד, mimi-echad, yes?
The moral is just don't do anything. Do until you get like
right before, you know, the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. טוב שלא תדור משתדור ולא תשלם. Tov shelo tiddor mishetiddor
velo tishaleim. That's the moral of the story.
No, but even if you're going to do it, just
do it a second before. Right, right. Okay, ומב' מינים תביא שש.
Umibais minim tavi shesh. Now let's say,
right, it was בן יונה ben yona and בן
יונה. ben yona. So bring six. Now why bring six? Because she
doesn't know which one she did first, right? That's the situation of
ב' מינים. bais minim. So here's the story. You bring all of
these together. One of these, the one, has to correspond to the
עולה ola of the obligation. So you bring these two pairs. What
should she bring to correspond to the עולה ola of an obligation?
A תור tor or a בן יונה? ben yona? So the answer
is it depends what her obligation what she brought initially as her
obligation. Right, what she ever brought number one here at the first
קרבן, korban, then even though the נדר neder wasn't fulfilled, she's now
going to have to bring the עולה ola of the first קרבן
korban plus everything else, right? So since she doesn't know what her
first קרבן korban was was it a תור tor or
בן יונה ben yona we
don't know which one she did first. And therefore to correspond to
the עולה ola of that first קרבן, korban, she needs a תור
tor or and a בן יונה, ben yona, so she knows she
gets the right corresponding עולה ola plus those two sets. So she
has to bring six.
So that's the strange part. In theory it would be fine if
she just brought five either way.
Like why No, she has to bring four because she doesn't know
what her נדר neder was, plus an עולה ola that corresponds to
the חטאת chatas of the obligation. But she already יצא. yatza. But
that was כעין נדר. ke-ein neder. כעין נדר Ke-ein neder says I'm
bringing them all together as one unit. Okay. So ומב' מינים תביא
שש. Umibais minim tavi shesh. Now, that was the easy part. נתנתו
לכהן. Nesanaso lekohein. Now she went ahead and she gave her two
sets to the כהן, kohein, okay? ואינה יודעת מה נתנה. Ve-eina yoda-as
mah nasana. I'm sorry. ואינה יודעת מה נתנה. Ve-eina yoda-as mah nasana.
And הלך הכהן ועשה ואינו יודע מה עשה. Halach hakohein ve-asa ve-eino
yode-a mah asa. Okay, so she doesn't know, did I give him
all תורים, torim, all בני יונה, benei yona, half and half? The
כהן kohein says I don't know if I did half above and
half below, I did all above, all below. Who knows? Who was
paying attention? Okay, so צריכה so you would think if you have
absolutely no idea, it was still back to this. Like what could
be more obligatory than this?
But the answer is there could be
something because this satisfies your עולה ola obligation. If the כהן kohein
did it all above let's say, she didn't satisfy her חטאת chatas
obligation. So there's we don't know, right? You need all of this
because I don't know, maybe he did them all below or whatever
it is, and then you satisfy your עולה ola obligation. But you
gotta bring at least a חטאת chatas because maybe it was all
above and she didn't do the חטאת. chatas. Okay? So, so, so
what? צריכה להביא ד' פרידים לנדרה. Tzricha lehavi daled peridim lenidra. four
units for her נדר, neder, okay, ושתים לחובתה, veshtayim lechovatah, two for
her חובה chova because based on what there
in a scenario where she did bring a חטאת, chatas, you know,
where one was below and it was the חטאת, chatas, that would
have established what the עולה ola would have to be, but we
don't know what the עולה ola would have to be.
Okay. וחטאת אחת vechatat achat and one חטאת. chatat. And here is
the question: one חטאת chatat or two? So here is the question:
If
does the חטאת chatas determine the עולה, ola, or does the
עולה ola determine- or does the first thing you do determine the
second thing you do?
Always have to
do the חטאת chatas first anyway, don't you? Well yes, but you
might not have. You might have brought them all above and they've
all become עולות. olot. So the position of חטאת אחת chatat achat
basically says that the חטאת chatas determines the עולה. ola. So since
you- so therefore you bring all of these above, okay? Like what
meaning let's say everything was brought above, whatever. If- why are we
bringing a חטאת? chatas?
We have to bring a חטאת. chatas.
Why in this scenario when it all got mixed up? Because we
say maybe it was all brought above as an עולה, ola, right?
So if it was all brought above as an עולה, ola, so
you've got a תור ובן יונה tor uven yona as an עולה,
ola, whatever, fine. Bring a חטאת, chatat, whichever one you want. You're
going to bring a תור tor as a חטאת. chatas. No problem.
In the scenario it was all brought above,
so one of the birds that was the תור tor that counts
that goes together with your חטאת. chatas. If you decided to bring
a בן יונה ben yona as your חטאת, chatas, then one of
the birds above that was a בן יונה ben yona that goes
together with your חטאת, chatas, okay? No problem. All right, so bring
whichever one you want, and that one, since the חטאת chatas determines
the set, that חטאת chatas will select from the ones you brought
above which one corresponds to it. I'm still a little confused.
Don't you have to bring two for חטאת chatas because it- maybe-
maybe it was brought in the wrong place and maybe it was
the wrong kind, right?
There's no- there's no right or wrong kind. It was always the
חטאת chatas you could choose, you could always choose for the חובה.
chova. You weren't מפרש mefaresh by the חובה. chova. The חובה chova
you could always choose what... So the first opinion is bring one
for חטאת. chatat. Why you bringing a חטאת? chatat? Because everything was
brought above. But what was brought above, you both have תור ובן
יונה tor uven yona brought above. It doesn't determine what the חטאת
chatas is going to bring. You do the חטאת chatat and that
חטאת chatat will define which will be the you know which one
of the things brought above will go with it. That's the first
opinion. וחטאת אחת. vechatat achat. בן עזאי אומר שתי חטאות: Ben Azzai
omer shtei chatatot: two חטאות. chatatot. Why two חטאות? chatatot? Because what
בן עזאי Ben Azzai says is is that it is not that
the חטאת chatas determines, it is the first thing that is brought
determines. Okay. So for בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, fine, you brought them
all above. But what the חטאת chatas has to be is defined
by the first one you brought above. Because the first one you
brought above is always defined- the first thing you brought is always
defined as your חובה. chova. So the first thing you brought above
was the עולה ola of your חובה chova and that defines the
מין min of the חטאת. chatat. You got it? So for בן
עזאי Ben Azzai you have to bring the חטאת chatas because maybe
nothing was brought as a חטאת. chatat. Okay. But is it open-ended
what you bring or is it determined? So for בן עזאי, Ben
Azzai, for the חכמים Chachamim it's open-ended, for בן עזאי Ben Azzai
it's determined based on the first עולה ola that you brought. And
therefore since you don't know what that was, you gotta bring two
חטאות. chatatot. All right, great. We went through that משנה, Mishna, everybody.
That was not so painful. I mean, I actually think that the
board was extremely helpful. Okay. So what did people do before they
had a whiteboard? Okay. אמר רבי יהושע: amar Rabbi Yehoshua: Yes, I
had a question actually. It's just gonna be...
yeah, go for it. Why can't she just brought her four over
again instead of going all through this, start all over again?
That is a great question, and that is actually the last line
of the משנה. Mishna. I mean the last line of the משנה
Mishna is is explaining the irony of it. That if she had
done the whole thing right, now actually it's you know because she
got mixed up. I mean it's actually not a total lot more
because if- because she forgot what she said she actually initially would
have had to bring six. If she had remembered she would have
had to bring four, if she forgot she had to bring six.
But even so, we went from initially bringing six to now you're
bringing eight, right? So because you- and we can't just say just
start again. You can't start again because you already got stuff messed
up, and that stuff determines what's left to be done, you know.
To validate the whole thing...
start over?
No. Since some of the stuff might have been כשר kasher and
that might determine what the other stuff has to be, right? If
the עולה ola was done first, it determines what the חטאת chatat
has to be, and now you can't choose what the חטאת chatat
has to be or whatever. So that's exactly the point that's made
at the end of the משנה. Mishna. You would think look, just
do it all again. And the answer is like no, you start
one way but you mess things up, that could actually lead to
even an expanded obligation. All right. So and that's exactly the point
that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua makes. That was a perfect segue.
It's almost like מעוות לא יוכל לתקון. meuvat lo yuchal litkon.
Exactly. אמר רבי יהושע זהו שאמרו: amar Rabbi Yehoshua zehu she’amru: Oh,
כשחי קולו אחד, keshchai kolo echad, you have a- you have like
a ram, when it's alive it makes one sound, you know, it...
and you know it whatever what sound...
בה beh I guess. And when it's made, when it dies, קולו
זין, kolo zayin, you can turn it into seven different sounds. You
use the horns for horns, you use the intestines for like strings
for a stringed instrument, you use the leather for a drum. So
something starts one way and then it gets messed up I guess,
I mean I don't exactly get the analogy, but I get the
analogy, but I don't exactly what is you know what the, how
helpful it is. But anyway, it starts one way and then it
turns into something expanded. So this started, if she had known what
she was doing and remembered or whatever, it would have started as
four birds. She forgot, boom, it became six. You messed it up,
boom, it became eight, you know? So it's because you keep on
messing up that that you know, so things can expand beyond where
they began from.
So do you דייק dyek that it's דווקא davka the סתמא stama
is דווקא davka רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? Is that based on the
fact that he says קולו שבע kolo shiva and not קולו שמונה?
kolo shemona?
No, no, no, it has nothing based with the content of it,
you
know, it's not because of, right, the מחלוקת. machlokes.
Yeah, but that's circular then.
We have to שבע shiva or שמונה. shemona. And then he says,
reflecting on what he just said, he says indeed one animal becomes
seven voices, not eight voices. I'm going to have to think about
that, but at least that's not what
the, but the רש''י Rashi certainly doesn't understand that it's based on
inferring what his פסק psak would have led to in this case.
It's general. It's just the very fact that the way he's talking,
זהו שאמרו. zehu she'amru. It's like an idiom. It's, no, you're allowed
to say an idiom, but I think the point would be you
know, there's some way, I can't put my finger on it,
that the גמרא Gemara
feels that this is like the voice of a narrator. Like he's
sort of, I guess it's like he's stepping back and reflecting on
it, you know? He's not saying like he's not saying like הרי
אמרו harei amru blah blah blah, like זהו שאמרו, zehu she'amru, he's
like stepping back and saying oh this thing we've been discussing, this
illustrates, you know, dot dot dot dot. So he hears that as
an authorial voice. So that means if רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is
the author of קינים, Kinnim, then the earlier discussion, which showed that
a משנה Mishnah in קינים Kinnim that something done above, done below,
does not count as a חטאת, chatas, shows that for רבי יהושע,
Rabbi Yehoshua, it doesn't really count as a חטאת. chatas. So the
גמרא Gemara says אימה eima fine you're right. אימה דאמר רבי יהושע
לאפוקי מידי מעילה. Eima de-amar Rabbi Yehoshua la-apokei midei me'ilah. When he
says if you do it above, you do it below, it's like
a חטאת, chatas, it's enough like a חטאת chatas that there's no
מעילה. me'ilah. But למסקי ליה לחובה מי אמר? le-maskei lei le-chovah mi
amar? He never said that it would actually fulfill your obligation, which
is what we read yesterday, okay, and now we actually read it
having had the pleasure of going through the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so
let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Now it's very
interesting to start a משנה Mishnah with parentheses, but basically there's a
question whether this line belongs in the משנה. Mishnah. רש''י Rashi has
it, I'll read it. כל הפסולים שמלקו מליקתם פסולה ואינה מטמא בבית
הבליעה. Kol ha-psulim she-malku melikatam psulah ve-einah metamei be-veit ha-baleia. So the
first is actually, you know, this would actually be helpful if this
were the first line in the משנה Mishnah because it actually tells
you the baseline הלכה. halacha. The baseline הלכה halacha is if you
do the מליקה melikah properly, although we've said before a normal מליקה
melikah on a normal bird would make it a נבלה. neveilah. And
the signal that it's a נבלה neveilah is if you swallow it,
you know, it makes you טמא. tamei. And the reason why I
think we use that as an example is the other thing you'd
say no, a נבלה neveilah is אסור asur to eat. But there
might be a bird here sacrificed that's אסור asur to eat because
it's an עולה. olah. Okay? So if we want to sort of
speak about the הלכה halacha that demonstrates it's a נבלה, neveilah, we're
not going to say that it's אסור asur to eat. The more,
the one that really shows it is whether when you swallow it,
it makes you טמא. tamei. So that is a substitute way of
saying it's a נבלה, neveilah, okay? So if you do it properly,
even though if you did a normal bird you did מליקה, melikah,
it would actually be a נבלה, neveilah, because you're doing a קרבן
korban מליקה melikah and that's what you're supposed to do, it's not
a נבלה. neveilah. That's point number one. כל הפסולים שמלקו מליקתם פסולה
ואינה מטמא בבית הבליעה. Kol ha-psulim she-malku melikatam psulah ve-einah metamei be-veit
ha-baleia. Okay, I'm sorry, כל הפסולים, kol ha-psulim, I don't know why
I just said that. Okay, what I just said is the right
rule but it's not the first line in the משנה. Mishnah. The
first line in the משנה Mishnah is a generic line leading into
the other lines. And the generic line is that's if you did
it right. If you did it right, it is not a נבלה.
neveilah. And then this first line in parentheses is כל הפסולים שמלקו,
kol ha-psulim she-malku, if you were somebody that shouldn't, you're פסול, pasul,
you're a non-כהן, Kohen, you're an אונן, onen, you're a whatever you
are, a בעל מום, baal mum, and you went ahead and you
did it. So now we'll say oh, somebody פסול pasul did the
מליקה, melikah, so that shouldn't count as a קרבן, korban, so that
should be like doing a מליקה melikah on a normal bird and
therefore should be a נבלה. neveilah. And the answer is guess what,
no, מליקתם פסולה ואינה מטמא בבית הבליעה. melikatam psulah ve-einah metamei be-veit
ha-baleia. Although the מליקה melikah is invalid and the קרבן korban is
invalid, since somehow the problem here was in the context of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and you might remember there's another whole set
of discussions, what may be here, pop quiz everybody, okay, what if
something was done פסול pasul in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in
what way, where did you see that it's nevertheless could be like
a little כשר? kasher? It's the first משנה. Mishnah. שלא לשמה? She-lo
lishmah? No no no no, really פסול, pasul, completely פסול, pasul, nobody
was יוצא yotzei as a קרבן, korban, okay, it doesn't get right
to be put on the מזבח. mizbeach. But there's a way in
which it's not, that if something happened, you're allowed to treat it
like אם עלו לא ירדו? im alu lo yerdu? If you put
it on the מזבח, mizbeach, you don't take it down. So there's
some sense of like okay, it's פסול pasul but it's not totally
out of bounds, and if somehow it got to the מזבח. mizbeach.
I have to research the answer to the question. And if somehow
it got to the מזבח mizbeach we're not going to remove it.
But if it was some type of a פסול pasul that was
seen as as started outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash not just
you did something wrong here let's say it was a בעל מום
baal mum then you know whatever there's a debate which of these
what falls into that really bad פסולים psulim then it's completely out
of bounds and it doesn't get to stay on the מזבח. mizbeiach.
So that's the discussion about what type of פסולים psulim would get
to stay on the מזבח mizbeiach if they were put there. So
it's a very similar question what type of פסולים psulim are so
out of bounds it's like this thing didn't happen at all in
the context of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and therefore the מליקה
melikah makes it a נבלה neveilah or what type of פסולים psulim
are fine it was done it was done wrong it doesn't count
as a קרבן korban but it was enough right that at least
the מליקה melikah is going to be seen as acceptable in the
sense that it's not a נבלה. neveilah. If you know the בריסקר
Brisker way maybe of saying this is what types of things make
it not a מליקה melikah at all and what types of things
make it a מליקה פסולה. melikah psulah. Okay is it a מליקה
melikah but it was invalid or was it completely not like a
מליקה. melikah. So that's one way of saying it although that doesn't
work by the normal הלכות halachos about whether it goes down off
the מזבח mizbeiach but anyway okay so that's the point of the
משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah says you know what even if the
person who was a non כהן kohen a בעל מום baal mum
whatever he was it was done in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
it was done as a מליקה melikah it was done on a
bird קרבן korban it's not a נבלה. neveilah. Okay that's the first
line of the משנה Mishnah and now we're going to have concrete
examples and that's the question whether the משנה Mishnah opened with a
general line or did it just open with the concrete examples. מלק
בשמאל malak b'smol let's say it was a כהן kohen I gave
you a more extreme case a non כהן kohen he uses his
left hand או בלילה o balailah you did it at night קרבנות
korbanot are only brought during the day okay so that would be
nevertheless it's not a נבלה. neveilah. Here are other cases which are
not a נבלה. neveilah. שחט חולין בפנים shachat chullin bifnim now this
is really shocking I went ahead and I brought my chicken okay
I wonder if חולין chullin just means I didn't sanctify it or
it means that it's not it's or what if it's like not
even of the right מין min that could ever be a קרבן.
korban. Let's make it I brought my pigeon my unsanctified pigeon into
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the כהן kohen did a מליקה
melikah on it. It wasn't a קרבן korban but it was a
pigeon in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that the כהן kohen you
know was done a מליקה melikah that's not a נבלה. neveilah. Okay
I do wonder really what would be the story if it was
like a duck or a chicken like how you know is it
just that it isn't sanctified you know if it's really not even
the מין min would that anyway but okay. He really should have
said מלק חולין בפנים malak chullin bifnim right? You're right you know
what I gotta pay attention to the words I'm reading I'm sorry
I made the mistake saying the מלק חולין בפנים malak chullin bifnim
is at the end and the מלק חולין בפנים malak chullin bifnim
actually oh I'm sorry I made a mistake the מלק חולין malak
chullin actually is a נבלה. neveilah. It's שחט חולין בפנים shachat chullin
bifnim thank you Michael. שחט shachat take it all back gotta go
edit the tape שחט חולין בפנים shachat chullin bifnim no actually we're
going to find it if you did a מליקה melikah and it
wasn't a קרבן korban it is it is it is a נבלה.
neveilah. The reason here is that you did a שחיטה shechitah so
then it's not such a חידוש. chiddush. The only חידוש chiddush is
that even if you did a שחיטה shechitah you know in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash at the end of the day it's still
a שחיטה. shechitah. Okay so שחט חולין בפנים shachat chullin bifnim if
you did a שחיטה shechitah וקדשים בחוץ v'kodshim bachutz let's say you
שחט shacht a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash a
bird קרבן. korban. So you might say it's a קרבן korban a
bird קרבן korban the only thing that's like recognized is מליקה melikah
I mean not supposed to bring it outside the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash but nevertheless anything other than מליקה melikah is inappropriate. No אינה
מטמא בבית הבליעה eina metamei b'veit habliah that's not טמא. tamei. So
basically okay so I'm sorry yeah I got I got I got
that confused to emphasize that the חידוש chiddush is the it's שחיטה
shechitah with a bird. Right exactly exactly but I mean obviously right
it was not a bird it's the thing you normally would do
מליקה. melikah. Okay so what do we have? We have פסולים psulim
who did it who did who did who did מליקת קדשים בפנים
melikat kodshim bifnim okay that but they're פסול pasul that's still going
to be not a נבלה neveilah and then we have okay מליקה
melikah of פסולים בפנים psulim bifnim okay the two concrete examples were
שמאל smol and לילה lailah we didn't discuss other examples. And then
we have the שחיטה shechitah of okay we either have חולין בפנים
chullin bifnim or קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz okay these are all birds
and because it is שחיטה shechitah even though like you know this
shouldn't be going on in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you don't
שחט חולין shacht chullin in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you don't
שחט shacht even קדשים kodshim birds in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
you shouldn't be שוחט shochet outside. Since it's שחיטה shechitah it's also
not a נבלה. neveilah. One wait minute let's finish the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay מלק בסכין malak besakin now let's say you actually did the
מליקה melikah in a way that's physically not the right מליקה melikah
you used a knife which isn't an act of מליקה. melikah. So
then it's just seen as a different act then it's just like
you you like you like tore off the neck you know that's
not even a מליקה. melikah. Okay מלק חולין בפנים וקדשים בחוץ malak
chullin bifnim v'kodshim bachutz so this is what I was confusing and
I read earlier okay so all of this is check not a
נבלה. neveilah. Here's what's the X and is a נבלה. neveilah. Let's
use a color. Okay the check is not a נבלה neveilah the
X is yes a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, מליקת חולין בפנים וקדשים בחוץ.
melikat chullin bifnim vekodashim bachutz. So this is what I was confusing
and I read earlier. Okay,
so all of this is check, not an עבירה. aveirah. Here's what's
the X that is an עבירה. aveirah. Let's change color. Okay, the
check is not an עבירה. aveirah. The X is yes an עבירה.
aveirah. So what is, first is מליקת סכין, melikat sakkin, which basically
is not even a מליקה. melika. That's just like tear, I'm just
gonna, that's like tearing off the head. This is the same point,
if you did, if you used a knife that's not a מליקה.
melika. Okay, and then we have מליקת חולין בפנים melikat chullin bifnim
and, right, am I getting this right, and קדשים בחוץ. kodashim bachutz.
So here the point is that if the מליקה, melika, when you
do a שחיטה shechita at the end of the day it's a
שחיטה, shechita, it's not a נבלה. neveila. When you do a מליקה,
melika, a מליקה melika maybe the כהן kohen could be פסול pasul
or whatever, but it needs to be a מליקה melika on קדשים
kodashim in the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. Okay, those are the key
elements. If you have a מליקה melika and if it's on קדשים,
kodashim, it's the right act on the right object in the right
place, then even if it's done in a way that it's פסול,
pasul, it's still gonna make it not a נבלה. neveila. Okay, but
it has to, if it's the wrong act, okay, so this gets,
this is not מליקה, melika, okay,
or it's the wrong place
or it's the wrong object, that's gonna be, that's gonna be considered
completely off bounds and therefore make it a נבלה. neveila.
שחיטת קדשים בחוץ, shechitat kodashim bachutz, that's
like, isn't that a כרת? kareit?
Yes, but that's not our point right now.
Right act, okay, right
object and in the right place. So even if it's פסול pasul
for
whatever reason, it's still a מליקה melika
that's not a נבלה. neveila. Okay, whereas this is wrong act, the
מליקת סכין. melikat sakkin. Okay, this is wrong object, חולין chullin and
this is wrong place. Any one of those makes it totally out
of bounds and makes it a נבלה. neveila. So just to understand,
I would get כרת kareit for שחיטת קדשים בחוץ, shechitat kodashim bachutz,
I'd get
כרת kareit for doing it but you, the bird would not be
a נבלה. neveila. But
if you ate it, you'd get any, you'd get a לאו, lav,
right? Yeah, but I just wouldn't be טמא. tamei. Now, תורים שלא
הגיע זמנם, torim shelo higia zemanan, okay, let's say the animal is
not fit yet to be a
קרבן. korban. So a תור, tor, the הלכה halacha
is that a תור tor has to be an adult and a
בן יונה ben yonah because of the word בן ben has to
be a child and the משנה mishnah describes like how, what's the
age of maturity, okay, you know,
בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, רשית אליה, reishat eliyah, anyway, that you know
whether it's one or the other. So if it's not yet old
enough or it's too old, תורים שלא הגיע זמנם ובני יונה
שעבר זמנם
torim shelo higia zemanan
uvenei yonah
sheavar zemanan or the בני יונה
benei yonah are too old, okay, so it's not the right age.
שיבשה גפה, sheyafsha gappa, let's say the wing is dried up.
שנסמית עינה, shenismat eina, the eye is poked out. שנקטעה רגלה, sheniktea
ragla, the leg is cut off. So by a bird a מום
mum is not enough. It needs to be מחוסר אבר. mechussar eivar.
It has to be lacking a limb. So lacking a limb, a
totally dried up wing even if it's not physically removed, it's like
it's not there. Cut off leg. But how about the eye thing?
So תוספות tosafot says the eye means that the eye is poked
out and that's the missing limb. But רש"י rashi says no, נסמית
nismat just means blind and רש"י rashi introduces a new idea, if
you look at רש"י rashi the second narrow line, שנסמית עינה, shenismat
eina, רש"י rashi says דהוי ליה מחוסר אבר, dehavei lei mechussar eivar,
והקריבהו נא לפחתך. vehakrivehu na lepachatekha. Okay, so רש"י rashi sort of,
it's like a funny רש"י rashi because he says מחוסר אבר mechussar
eivar which sounds like he's sort of reading it like תוספות tosafot
that the eye is really, but then he says והקריבהו נא לפחתך.
vehakrivehu na lepachatekha. Why do you have to give this idea? I
mean the גמרא gemara learns out a problem of מחוסר אבר, mechussar
eivar, if you remember from נח, noach, from it says, you know,
החיה אתך hechaiya itcha whatever. And anyway, so it sounds a little
bit like רש"י rashi is saying because the eye is not functional,
that counts as מחוסר אבר mechussar eivar and we read מחוסר אבר
mechussar eivar a little bit more broadly and not just in the
physical sense because of this idea of והקריבהו נא לפחתך. vehakrivehu na
lepachatekha.
That's sort of the way I'm reading the juxtaposition in רש"י.
rashi. But תוספות tosafot says no, no, no, we're talking only that
the eye is poked out. Okay, but רש"י rashi sort of sounds
like a non-functional eye for this הלכה halacha would count as מחוסר
אבר. mechussar eivar. Alright, anyway, ומטמא בבית הבליעה. umitammei beveit habeliah. All
of those cases, it is a נבלה. neveila. Okay, so if it
basically, if the, so if, so this idea, right object or whatever,
included in the right object is that it has to be, right,
if it's here is let's say, you know, if it's a chicken,
the example I was given, if it's a chicken or if it's
a too young or it's a מחוסר אבר, mechussar eivar, all of
those things are another example of wrong object. Okay, so wrong act,
wrong place, or wrong object. Either it's חולין chullin or it's not
the right type of animal, okay, or it's בעל מום baal mum
or whatever it is, those are the things that it is not
considered a good מליקה. melika. Which is not so helpful because it's
a very abstract, which is what a כלל klal is supposed to
be, but it's still not so helpful. Anything that the פסול psul
happened in the קודש kodesh context, in the מקדש mikdash context, that's
enough inbounds and it's a good מליקה, melika, even if it's not
a good קרבן korban and it's not a נבלה. neveilah. If it's
not related to the מקדש mikdash context, it's out of bounds and
it's not a good מליקה melika and it is a נבלה. neveilah.
Now what I said was much more specific, I mean it was
abstract but it was much more specific. Place, act, object. That we
got. If you try to apply that rule of is it במקדש
bemikdash or not, בקודש bakodesh or not בקודש, bakodesh, it would not
make sense. Like why is somebody using his left hand and doing
it at night? Okay, let's see if this works. This is פסול
בקודש psul bakodesh because when you got it in, it could have
been done in the right way. Whereas when you brought in the
chicken or the too young or the מחוסר אבר, mechusar eiver, there
was no way it could have been done right. What if it
got- what if it lost the limb inside the בית המקדש? Beit
HaMikdash? The מליקת סכין melikat sakin versus the שמאל לילה smol lyla
is where the- yeah, I guess that's true. Like this is something
you did wrong, the same way doing it with your left hand
is doing it wrong. Right? Why is מליקה melika with the left
hand and מליקה melika with a סכין sakin different? We could say,
that's a good point. We could say, no, definitionally with your hand
is a מליקה, melika, without your hand is not a מליקה. melika.
But that's not a question of פסולה בקודש. psulah bakodesh. Right? At
the end of the day, you're exactly right. That exactly shows I
have my bird here, I have it in and everything is right.
If I use my left hand it's פסולה בקודש. psulah bakodesh. If
I'm using my knife it's not פסולה. psulah. So the פסולה בקודש
psulah bakodesh is not the best way of abstracting, you know, conceptualizing
the differences. It might explain a lot of it, but whether it
explains all of it is a question. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב שמואל, Amar Rav Shmuel, says Ra- actually
אמר רב, Amar Rav, אוי אוי אוי, oy oy oy, it's one
of those mornings. אמר רב: Amar Rav: שמאל ולילה אינו מטמא בבית
הבליעה. smol velyla eino metamei beveit habalia. Okay, that's our משנה. mishna.
Night and the left hand, it's still okay, not a נבלה. neveilah.
זר וסכין מטמא בבית הבליעה. zar vesakin metamei beveit habalia. So what
he added that wasn't in the משנה mishna is the זר. zar.
If a non-כהן kohen did it, that would be considered to be
completely out of bounds. That's like a knife. Now by the way,
here's why it makes sense. It's not normally the problem of a
non-כהן kohen doing an עבודה. avodah. Why is a non-כהן kohen different
than somebody who's like a פסול, pasul, although this פסולים psulim seems
to explain people, but here's the point. Because the object of- what
is the object of מליקה? melika? The object used to do the
act. Fingernail. Whose fingernail? The כהן's kohen fingernail. That's like- it's like
a- whose fingernail? The כהן's kohen fingernail. So a non-כהן- kohen it's
not the general problem. A non-כהן's kohen fingernail is like using a
knife. It's like ripping it off with your bare hands. It's the
wrong object. That might be the קודש kodesh aspect of that- the
כהן's kohen right hand. Right, but anybody's left hand, that's the interesting
thing. His left hand, since it's still a כהן's kohen hand, that's
considered the right object. But somehow anyway a non-כהן kohen is like
a סכין, sakin, because and again part of this has to do
with not the just general פסול psul of a non-כהן, kohen, but
because that- the- the knife here is the כהן's kohen thumb. Okay?
So a non-כהן kohen is- is like a- סכין. sakin. That's what
he's saying. Okay. זר וסכין מטמא בבית הבליעה. zar vesakin metamei beveit
habalia. מאי שנא שמאל דאיתא הכשר ביום הכפורים? mai shna smol deitah
hechsher beyom hakippurim? So the גמרא Gemara says, wait wait wait, what's
the difference here? Why are these some things more kosher, more in
the realm of being kosher than others? Okay, because presumably what shows
it's not totally out of bounds is that sometimes this can work
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay? So why do you say
שמאל smol is- left hand is not totally out of bounds? Because
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur the כהן kohen uses his left hand,
right, when he does the קטורת, ketoret, he's got one with his
right hand, one with his left hand, the גחלים. gechalim. ולילה, velyla,
why is לילה lyla not totally out of bounds? דאיתא הכשר באברים
ופדרים, deitah hechsher be'evarim upedarim, because you burn the fats and the
limbs at night. So if the idea is that sometimes it's- it's
inbounds and that should make it okay, so זר נמי איתא הכשר
בשחיטה? zar nami itah hechsher beshchita? So a זר zar also sometimes
works, right, by שחיטה, shchita, non-כהנים kohanim when you're dealing with שחיטה,
shchita, not מליקה, melika, they do שחיטה. shchita. So he's not totally
out of bounds? So as opposed to the more specific way we
were looking at it is right object, right act, what makes it
an act of מליקה, melika, the כהן's kohen fingers opposed to a
non-כהן's kohen finger, the גמרא Gemara is looking at it just more
generally. Is this something that sometimes works? If it's something that sometimes
works, that should be enough to make it not a נבלה. neveilah.
So he says look, a זר zar also sometimes works, right, by
שחיטה. shchita. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שחיטה לאו עבודה היא,
shchita lav avodah hi, שחיטה shchita isn't considered one of the עבודות.
avodot. Why? Well, this is always the funny thing. Is it not
an עבודה avodah because it can be done by a זר, zar,
that proves it's not an עבודה? avodah? Or is it not an
עבודה avodah somewhere else? Because if you think about it, right, so
many of the פסולים psulim about פיגול pigul and all that type
of stuff, right, start at the moment of שחיטה. shchita. So what
does it mean to say it's not an עבודה? avodah? What it
means to say is you don't need a כהן. kohen. So then
when I ask you, oh, can't I prove- it's a little circular.
Anyway. Yeah, there's a third explanation. שחיטה לאו עבודה היא shechita lav
avoda hi because it's not קודש. kodesh. Right? Unlike מליקה. melika. מליקה
melika is unique to the קודש. kodesh. What do you mean? What
does that mean, unique to the? We don't do... Oh, you mean,
oh you mean one... That's an interesting point. Oh, that's a nice
read. So so so, oh so you're saying is שחיטה לאו עבודה
היא shechita lav avoda hi means that we we don't conceptually think
of it as an עבודה avoda because as opposed to קבלה, kabala,
זריקה, zrika, הולכה, holacha, this is something that we always do when
we need to eat meat. So there's nothing that makes it a...
Right, that's a nice point. I hadn't thought about that. That's a
nice point. Okay, שחיטה לאו עבודה היא. shechita lav avoda hi. No,
we don't think of שחיטה shechita as an עבודה, avoda, and therefore
the fact that a זר zar can do it is not sort
of indicative of the fact that a זר zar is not so
bad. Okay? So because שחיטה shechita is its own category. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא? velo? Really? והאמר רבי זירא, ve-ha-amar Rabbi Zeira,
שחיטת פרה בזר פסולה. shechitat para be-zar psula. If if a non-כהן
kohen shechts the פרה אדומה, para aduma, it's invalid. Okay? ומחוי רב
לן, u-machvei Rav lan, רב Rav signaled with his hands to say
the indication of this was אלעזר וחוקה. Elazar ve-chuka. So because in
the תורה Torah and it says that אלעזר הכהן Elazar Ha-Kohen should
take the פרה אדומה para aduma and it says זאת חוקת התורה.
zot chukat ha-Torah. So that means it's only done right exactly this
way. What? I don't I also wonder, maybe maybe they had sign
language then. Anyway, so maybe there was a guy in the in
the שיעור shiur whose name was אלעזר. Elazar. Anyway, anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says so if you need שחיטה shechita even by a
פרה אדומה para aduma and I should say excuse me you need
שחיטת כהן. shechitat kohen. So the fact that there's times that you
need כהן, kohen, that shows that it is in the category of
עבודה. avoda. And therefore the fact that ninety-nine percent of the time
you use a זר, zar, that says that sometimes a זר zar
is כשר kasher to do an עבודה. avoda. Since one percent of
the time you require a כהן, kohen, that gets it categorized as
an עבודה, avoda, and therefore it becomes a הלכה, halacha, זר zar
is כשר kasher to do this עבודה. avoda. Okay? But the גמרא
Gemara says no, no, no, you can't bring any proof from פרה
אדומה. para aduma. פרה אדומה para aduma is sui genre... it's not
sui genre... how do you pronounce it? Sui generis? Anyway, it's its
own category. שאני פרה דקדשי בדק הבית היא. shani para de-kadshei bedek
ha-bayit hi. פרה para is completely bizarre. פרה para is not even
a קרבן. korban. Okay? It doesn't it's not brought in the בית
המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. It has קדושה, kedusha, but it's קדושת בדק הבית.
kedushat bedek ha-bayit. It's not קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. So if you
need a כהן, kohen, it's not evidence that it's an עבודה. avoda.
There are things you need כהנים kohanim for that are not עבודות.
avodot. What's something you need a כהן kohen for that's not an
עבודה? avoda? מצורע? metzora? צרעת? tzara'at? Excellent. So the גמרא Gemara says
the very fact that it's out of the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash
and not you know and it's and it's not a קרבן, korban,
then therefore you can't use the כהן kohen as proof it's an
עבודה. avoda. It's the opposite. It's a דווקא davka non-קרבן korban and
the כהן kohen is coming for some because some there are some
non-עבודות avodot that need a כהן. kohen. Okay? So, so ולא כל
דכן הוא? ve-lo kol de-chen hu? But the גמרא Gemara says wait,
it's a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. קדשי בדק הבית בעו כהונה? kadshei
bedek ha-bayit ba'u kehuna? If a non-קרבן korban requires a כהן, kohen,
קדשי מזבח מיבעיא? kadshei mizbeach mibaya? Certainly a קרבן? korban? So no,
אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, amar Rav Sheshet brei de-Rav Idi,
מידי דהוי אמרות נגעים. midi de-havei amara'ot nega'im. No, like looking at
צרעת. tzara'at. דלאו עבודה היא ובעי כהונה. de-lav avoda hi u-ba'ei kehuna.
It's not an עבודה avoda it needs a כהן. kohen. So שחיטה
shechita as as for קרבנות korbanot never needs a כהן. kohen. Since
שחיטה shechita for קרבנות korbanot never needs a כהן, kohen, you can't
say look, a זר zar is כשר kasher to do this עבודה.
avoda. It's not an עבודה! avoda! Okay? So we never find a
זר zar כשר kasher to do an עבודה, avoda, and that's why
we're going to say that if a זר zar does the מליקה,
melika, it's totally out of bounds and it's a נבילה. neveila. Okay?
That's the argument. But the גמרא Gemara isn't done. The גמרא Gemara
says ונילף מבמה? ve-neilef mi-bama? So the גמרא Gemara says why not
learn from a במה? bama? There's no כהונה kehuna בבמה be-bama and
you can use so a זר zar is כשר kasher בבמה. be-bama.
So the גמרא Gemara says מבמה לא ילף. mi-bama lo yalef. Nah,
במה bama isn't relevant. Okay? What you do outside of the בית
המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash is not relevant for when certain things can be...
Some things aren't so bad sometimes they're כשר. kasher. If they're outside
the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash that's a completely irrelevant discussion. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא? velo? והתניא, ve-hatanya, מנין ליוצא שאם עלה לא
ירד? minayin le-yotzei she-im ala lo yered? How do you know if
something was taken out of the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash and then
you put it on the altar you don't take it down? That
was that other thing about things are how bad are they, you
know, when they get up they don't come down. How do you
know that applies to יוצא yotzei meat that was taken out of
the בית המקדש? Beit Ha-Mikdash? שהרי יוצא כשר בבמה. she-harei yotzei kasher
be-bama. Because by במה bama you don't have even a concept of
יוצא. yotzei. So here you see you're using the reality of the
במה bama to indicate how bad a פסול psul is. So it's
very relevant. So let's say the using a זר zar is on
a במה bama shows you it's not such a huge פסול. psul.
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says no. תנא זאת תורת העולה סמיך
ליה. tana zot torat ha-ola samich lei. The we're not really saying
that יוצא yotzei is כשר kasher because of במה. bama. That's just
like an אסמכתא. asmachta. It really we're not learning from במה bama
that taking it out of the environs of the בית המקדש Beit
Ha-Mikdash is not so bad. We have a פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק
pasuk says זאת תורת העולה, zot torat ha-ola, תורה אחת לכל העולים.
Torah achat le-chol ha-olim. Pretty much anything that goes on the altar
gets to stay there. If you want to take something off the
altar, you've got to prove how that it's terrible. I don't have
to prove that it's good, why why it's not so bad, you
have to prove that it's... so bad that it deserves to be
taken off. So we really don't have to prove the case of
יוצא. yotzei. יוצא yotzei gets to stay on the מזבח mizbeach because
you can't prove to me that it's so bad. I don't need
to learn it from a במה. bama. So the גמרא Gemara is
saying basically you can't really learn something from a במה. bama. So
the reason שחיטת shchitas מליקת זר melikas zar is off-bounds is that
a זר zar is never כשר kosher to do an עבודה. avoda.
שחיטה shchita isn't an עבודה, avoda, במה bama isn't relevant, since there's
never a scenario that a זר zar is כשר kosher to do
an עבודה, avoda, מליקת melikas זר zar is totally out of bounds
and therefore a נבלה. neveila. That's the position of רב. Rav. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says רבי יוחנן אמר Rebbi Yochanan amar but
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan disagree. זר אין מטמא בית הבליעה, zar ein
metamei beis hablia, סכין מטמא בית הבליעה. sakin metamei beis hablia. No,
the knife, you're right, that's our משנה, mishna, but a זר zar
is included in the פסולים. psulim. Okay, and if it's a non-כהן,
kohen, it's also, it's still the right act, the right object, the
right place. I don't care that the doer is wrong, okay, it's
still going to be okay and it's not going to be a
נבלה. neveila. Okay, so סכין מטמא. sakin metamei. תנן, tnan, now let's
see which side we can prove based on our משנה. mishna. כל
הפסולים שמלקו מליקתן פסולה. kol hapsulim shemalku melikatan psula. All the ones
that did it, it is invalid. Okay, so that was our opening
generic line. All the so, בשלמא bishlama לרבי יוחנן, leRebbi Yochanan, כל
העשוי על ידי זר. kol ha'asuy al yedei zar. For רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan that generic line, because the משנה mishna explicitly said שמאל
ולילה. smol velaila. So why would we say this actually is the
line that was in parentheses, right? So it seems like, you know,
that the גמרא Gemara had that line. So why if we explicitly
said שמאל ולילה, smol velaila, what would a generic line be saying
כל הפסולים? kol hapsulim? So that's coming to include for רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan a זר. zar אלא לרב, ela leRav, כל לאתויי מאי?
kol l'asuyei mai? For רב, Rav, what does the word כל kol
come to include? לאתויי שמאל ולילה? l'asuyei smol velaila? Doesn't it come
to include מה לאו, ma lav, shouldn't we say לאתויי שמאל ולילה?
l'asuyei smol velaila? No, you can't say that. שמאל ולילה בהדיא קתני.
smol velaila behedya katani. No, it's coming to to say night, no,
night and night and left is said explicitly. That can't be what
the generic opening statement is saying. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
תני ובתר הכי מפרש. tani uvasar hachi mefaresh. No, כל הפסולים, kol
hapsulim, we make a generic statement and then we say what do
I mean when I say a פסול pasul makes it not נבלה.
neveila. Specifically what I mean is like a כלל ופרט, klal uprat,
specifically what I mean is שמאל ולילה. smol velaila. I don't really
mean to include more than I've already beyond what I'm actually going
to say. Okay, so for רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan the generic, the
umbrella statement includes a זר, zar. and for רב Rav the umbrella
statement is just meant to be specified by night and night and
your left hand and does not include anything more. Okay, now but
the גמרא Gemara is going to continue. תא שמע, ta shema, come
in here. זה הכלל. zeh haklal. כל שהיה פסולו בקודש, kol shehaya
psulo bakodesh, that last line, right, that made this פסולו בקודש psulo
bakodesh idea. אינו מטמא בגדים בית הבליעה. eino metamei bgadim beis hablia.
So anything that its invalidity was in the קודש. kodesh. So what
more is that including that we haven't said? בשלמא bishlama לרבי יוחנן,
leRebbi Yochanan, כל העשוי על ידי זר. kol ha'asuy al yedei zar.
Again, anything that went wrong in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would
mean okay, even if a non-כהן kohen did it, for רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan that's included in still not נבלה. neveila. אלא לרב ela
leRav לאתויי מאי, l'asuyei mai, but for רב Rav what else are
we including? So the גמרא Gemara says ולטעמיך, ultameich, according to you,
how about the second part of that line? שלא היה פסולו בקודש,
shelo haya psulo bakodesh, if the פסול psul happened out of the
context of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, לאתויי מאי, l'asuyei mai, what's
the you know, that that is a נבלה, neveila, what more is
that including? אלא, ela, I'll tell you what these lines are including.
רישא לאתויי שחיטת קדשים בפנים. reisha l'asuyei shchitas kodshim bifnim. When we
say as long as it's in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you're
okay, you know what that's including? We didn't mention, we mentioned שחיטת
חולין בפנים וקדשים בחוץ. shchitas chullin bifnim vekodshim bachutz. What we didn't
mention is קדשים בפנים. kodshim bifnim. A bird עולה, ola, so it's
actually a קרבן, korban, and מליקה melika is what is obligated in
it. So you might think you're חייב chayav to do מליקה, melika,
you've got the bird קרבן korban in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
maybe שחיטה shchita there's considered such a perversion that it makes it
נבלה. neveila. No, at the end of the day it's still שחיטה.
shchita. So the thing that's added to פסולו בקודש psulo bakodesh that
is not נבלה neveila is plus שחיטה, shchita, excuse me, plus plus
קדשים בפנים. kodshim bifnim. That's what's added by the כלל. klal. As
long as you're doing שחיטה, shchita, חולין בפנים, chullin bifnim, קדשים בחוץ,
kodshim bachutz, or even קדשים kodshim which clearly require מליקה, melika, all
of this is still פסולו בקודש. psulo bakodesh. That's what's added by
that to say that it's not נבלה. neveila. And what's the last
line added? אלא רישא לאתויי שחיטת קדשים בפנים, ela reisha l'asuyei shchitas
kodshim bifnim, סיפא לאתויי מליקת חולין בחוץ. seifa l'asuyei melikas chullin bachutz.
So here we have מליקת חולין בפנים, melikas chullin bifnim, קדשים בחוץ
kodshim bachutz plus obviously, I mean it's no big חידוש, chidush, מליקת
חולין בחוץ melikas chullin bachutz is you just rip the head off
of your chicken, but okay, you know, plus plus חולין. chullin. So
basically these general זה הכלל zeh haklal lines are not including really
that much more than we would have known, and whether a זר,
zar, the מליקת melikas זר zar, is a נבלה neveila or not
נבלה neveila remains a debate of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן. Rebbi
Yochanan. And one way of thinking about it is how much is
it just a problem of a non-כהן kohen and then you would
say so that falls just in the פסול... psul... פסולים psulim category.
And how much would you say it's a problem of the wrong
object? And then it becomes a type of a thing of like
using the knife. So I think that's a way of understanding exactly
what that debate is: are we just have the wrong person or
do we actually hear the person is the object and the object's
person and is actually the wrong object as well. Okay, we will
end.